Preliminary Guide to the Gelman Library Media Resources Department records, 1968-1987 RG0106
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Gelman Library Media Resources Department records
1968-1987
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Gelman Library. Media Resources Dept.
RG0106
1.75 Linear Feet
Materials in this collection include correspondence, memos, articles, and handbooks. These materials cover the dates 1968 to 1987.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
In 1993 these materials were transferred to the University Archives by the Head of the Media Resources Department.
Historical or Biographical Note
As a department within Gelman Library, the Media Resources Department maintains and circulates the audio/video collection of the University. It is also responsible for supporting and assisting patrons in the use of two media classrooms and a student viewing/listening room on the lower level of the library. The head of the department reports to the Associate University Librarian for Information Services for Public Services.
Before 1979 it was known as the Audiovisual Department, and also used to house microfilms of newspapers and magazines. It also housed the Television News Study Center (which existed from 1979-87), which included abstracts of television news programs from the Vanderbilt University and CBS News archives, among others.
The George Washington University's Melvin Gelman Library opened in 1973. Before the Gelman Library (which received its current name in 1980), the University Library was located in Lisner Hall, formerly Lisner Library. When the University moved to Foggy Bottom in 1912 from its location on 15th and H Streets, N.W., the first library was located in the original Lisner Hall, the former St. Rose's School for Orphaned Girls, between 20th and 21st Streets on G Street. Other libraries include the Virginia Campus Library (established n 1990), and the Mount Vernon Campus Eckles Library (under GW control since 1997). Together, these three libraries form the Gelman Library System (GLS).
The Library is headed by a University Librarian, who oversees: the Assistant University Librarian, Administration, Development, and Personnel; Associate University Librarian for Collections Services; Associate University Librarian for Information Technology; Associate University Librarian for Public Services; Directors of the Mt. Vernon and Virginia Campus libraries, and the Manager of GLS (Gelman Library System) Financial Operations.
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include correspondence, memos, articles, and handbooks. These materials cover the dates 1968 to 1985. The files contains material about a variety of 7 subjects including the 1968 and 1972 political conventions, Iranian hostage project/media coverage of hostage, conference on study of television news. These files were from the Television News Study Center part of the Television News Archive collection at Vanderbilt University.
Collection Organization
Organized into two series Television News Study Center and projects; and Television News Study Center, records.
Hostages; Listening room; Conferences; Political conventions; Foggy Bottom (Washington, D.C.); Washington (D.C.); George Washington University; George Washington University. Library; Gelman Library. Television News Study Center; Gelman Library. Reserves and Media Resources Dept.
- Television News Study Center records, 1968-1985; RG0106 Series 1; 1.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes correspondence, project files, articles, memos, and publicity. This material dates from 1968-80. This material comes from the Television News Study Center, a research center in Gelman library. Formerly ACC#182
  - Vanderbilt Audio/video tape inventory (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - VTNA Collection: 1968 Convention (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - VTNA Collection: 1972 Convention (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - TV News Study Center-Proposals for policies (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Television News Study Center-Guide/publicity (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - TVNSC: Activities (Box 1, Folder 6)
    General note
    Miscellaneous
  - Television News Study Center (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - TVNSC brochure (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - TVNSC: Conference regarding study of TV news (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - TVNSC Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - TVNSC expense reports (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - TVNSC (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - TVNSC grant proposal (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Rough draft
  - TVNSC grant and opening of Center (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Vanderbilt videotape (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - TVNSC Guide (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - TVNSC Guide, articles, and publicity (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - TVNSC handbook (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - TV News inquiries (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - TVNSC Inquiries, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - TVNSC: Hostage Project, publicity (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, Media Analysis Project (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - TVNSC: Media Analysis Project and Michael Robinson, publicity (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - TVNSC: Media Analysis Project (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - TVNSC: Miscellaneous articles written by Fay Schreibaum (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - TVNSC: Publicity and articles (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - TVNSC: TV News Index and Abstracts, mailing list (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - TVNSC: TV News Index and Abstracts (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - TVNSC: Grant, miscellaneous equipment, and information (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Letters with complimentary copies of Television Network News (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Book reviews (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Ordered book in 1977 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - VTNA: Orders received (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - VTNA: Miscellaneous Information regarding the Archive (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - VTNA: Application forms (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - VTNA: Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Agreement between Vanderbilt TV News Archives and GWU Library Regional Center (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Telecommunications Information Center (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - MCHPP Grant (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Media Coverage regarding Hostage Tapes (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Articles regarding TV coverage of election (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - SCAIFE Grant budget (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - SCAIFE Grant proposal (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Television News Study Center and projects, 1975 ca.-1987; RG0106 Series 2; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series contains guides, memorandums, news articles, news releases, an invitation, correspondence, and brochures. The materials range in date from approximately 1975 to 1987. They cover the holdings of the Media Resources Department, transcription projects, and the Television News Study Center. Formerly vertical files
  - Library, University--Media Resources, 1975-08/1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Library, University--Television News Study Center, 07/21/1977-02/01/1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)